Hello community. Today we have a very
short video. We compare here our SDK our
orchestration of multi- aent behavior
with an in context learning of multi-
aent behavior. And you might say wait a
minute we have been told that to build
complex AI system and multi- aent system
you need a complex orchestration you
need I don't know what you go with lang
graph or crew AI or any specialized SDK
from Google or open AI whatever you
prefer but now today we have a new paper
from the University of Melbourne and
they kind of dropped here a little bit
of a bombshell because they said for the
most task those frameworks here are
actually making your EI performance
worse.
Here we have the study published April
30th, 2026 in context prompting
obsoletes agent orchestration in
procedural tasks. And this is here
University of Melbourne, but you also
see I14. [snorts] And whenever I see a
company or a startup or I don't know
what it is, I only see one University of
Melbourne. I'm a little bit skeptical.
No. So I had a look for you. Okay.
Professor Simon Dennis is the chief
scientific officer. He served as the
director of the complex human data hub
at the University of Melbourne at the
cognitive uh science center at Ohio
State University. So I would say okay I
think he knows what they are doing here.
Beautiful. So let's assume that they
have here the competence and the
knowledge about AI. Beautiful.
So let's have a look agent orchestration
frameworks. Now whatever you go no
langraph curi Google ADK open AIS agent
SDK Microsoft semantic kernel Amazon
strands and llama index my goodness no
but all more or less do the same thing
now you have an external orchestrator
agent an intelligence that sits above
all the other LLM the worker LLM's
tracking here the conversation state and
injecting now routing instruction at
every turn it is really here the boss if
you want now you Remember here from
December 2025 there was an empirical
study of agent developing practices here
in AI agent framework and the message
was that 80% of the human developer
reported difficulties in identifying the
frameworks especially that best meet
their specific development requirements.
So just some months ago more or less
from China Germany we had no idea here
so what exactly what model should I use
now? What a genantic orchestration
methodology should I use now for my
specific topic? And here in this paper
from 2025 they have here for basic
orchestration here lang chain lang
graphs dematic kernel for multi- aent
collaboration curi matpd autogen data
processing llama index. So they tried to
build here solution around this
however in this new study now this is
interesting. So we have now a clawson
set 4.5 as the main if you want
reasoning engine and now they build two
scenarios and the first scenario that
they build is a lang graph orchestrated
scenario we implement the orchestration
condition here here orchestrating all
the multiple AI agents using the lang
graph methodology. So this simply means
each flowchart node maps to a langraph
graph node and when the graph execution
reaches here an agent node that node
prompt template is inserted into the
system prompt before now calling the
specific LLM and at decision hubs the
orchestrator makes here an additional
LLM call to select which edge to follow
based on the conversation history the
available conditions of the system and
everything that you know so langraph I
personally have not used lang in graph
now for more than a year. So okay, I go
here with whatever the authors here of
this paper tell us and their results
from their experiments
and they compare this now to something
else to in context baseline. So this
means the core LLM of your agent and
they say you know what we don't need all
this scaffolding around here our core
LLM we trust here the intelligence of
the LLM and we just do in context
baselining. So the model receives here
the entire serialized flowchart in the
system prompt and we'll give you an
example. So this means really all the
node all the edges all the conditions
and the terminal state here rendered as
structured text and this is not
interesting and the model then the
multimodel coordination is self
orchestrated
so there's no external state tracking no
routing the calls so we have one API
called pair agent turn this is it and
now the big question is how much better
is one of those condition and if it is
really true like all the companies is an
SDK tell us no you have to use our
orchestration idea they now challenge
this and they are really transparent
they say hey look here's our prompt
system here from April 30 2026 this is
the agent system prompt so both
conditions yeah use the same base system
prompt per domain to be comparable so in
the langu condition the orchestrator
additional injected the current note
prompt template it turn and they go here
for three tests the first is a travel
booking No, something you're familiar
with. You're a helpful travel booking
assistant. Clear. Handle it gracefully.
Great. Then Zoom support. Your
specialist for Zoom calls and you
support your older user with diagnosing
the problems and suggesting solutions
for the Zoom features and settings and
issues or beautiful technical support.
And then insurance claims. This is
interesting. They tell the hey you are
an experienced insurance claim
specialist. help the policy holder file
and process their insurance claims by
gathering the necessary information,
verify the coverage, assess the damage
and guide them through the complete
settlement process. No, so multiple
agents now are starting to work.
Beautiful. But all of them have more or
less the same prompt structure. No, only
of course in the in context condition
here, the full serialized flowchart as I
told you all note, edges, conditions is
now appended here to the system prompt.
But otherwise it is really I think
comparable from the way they build their
experiment.
Here you have as I told you they are
really transparent here the in context
prompt. This is here for the travel uh
examples. So the model is not just
chatting along. No it is really
executing a serialized state machine
that it holds entirely in its own
memory. And as you know half a year ago
people were skeptical that here the m
can really hold this if we have 10 20 50
steps here
of this procedure in its in context
learning memory if it's really if we can
trust this model. So they tell us hey in
the in context condition this model
receives the entire serialized flowchart
in the system prompt we have 6,000
characters in total. tell the model
instructor to follow the procedure step
by step without mentioning that it is
following a script and here you go. So
you have really all the information
available and they show you here for the
insurance claim they really go here with
55 nodes, six decision hubs, five
terminal states. So they really build up
here the complex crop structure and they
say the scientific takeaway is that the
modern frontier models like a claude 4.5
this is the models when they started
their tests can see this entire map in
their context and navigate it
holistically. So they say when we use no
orchestration we chop this map into tiny
little pieces for it for each particular
node which causes now tell us the order
the I model to lose the global
conversation arc. Now this is an
interesting statement because I thought
the more complex it gets the more
detailed I should be and the more
separating here the complexity in lower
in multiple lower complexity entities
would be here the successful operation
and they tell us no exactly the opposite
is true interesting so I want to show
you just the results you have all the
information here in the paper they just
tell us and this is a quote from the
paper up Frontier model given the entire
procedure in its system prompt like here
our entropic model and left to self
orchestrate consistently outperforms the
very same model when orchestrated via a
lang graph across every domain and
across every metric we tested. Now this
is a this is a strong statement because
this tells us you know what our llams
our core of the agents become so
intelligent is now so instruction
falling in its memory in its in context
learning and its prompt structure that
we don't need langraph anymore
they tell us you know what it
outperforms any other SDK with langraph
or crewi whatever they tested here and
they have a better metric here success
metric and whatever we tested here as a
domain and I showed you travel and
insurance and whatever they outperform
here language
is this now really the time when we say
okay our latest huge frontier model are
they really now so good that we can
trust them we don't have to build the
scaffolding around those AI the harness
around the AI interesting
and here you have to numerical results.
So for the travel domain 14 nodes, for
the zoom domain also 14 nodes and for
the insurance as I showed you 55 nodes
they have now defined criteria and
everything and measure everything and
you just see for in context here it's
bold. So it performs in every dimension
in every aspect in every task here
everything from length graph. So just
providing here all the complete
information in the prompt you get a
better result than you would build here
the orchestration agent or orchestration
multi- aent system.
Interesting.
And they tell us here for the travel
booking there's something special
because the complex agent framework here
with langraph failed 24% of the time
mostly due to handoff errors. Of course,
if you have extreme conversation, know
sometimes it can introduce an error, a
hallucination, some whatever. And they
said the single prompt model, the ICL
model, the second model stayed on track,
proving that the more we try to help the
AI model with some external code, the
more we actually get in its way.
Now, this is an interesting statement.
Does it really mean that all this
scaffolding is just a distraction now
and that we can trust our foundational
models here, our LLMs more and more?
Interesting. Absolutely interesting. And
they give us here the failure rates
across the domains here and conversation
and everything. Just look here at zoom
here now 14 nodes. So a normal structure
would say in context failures detected
one lang graph failures detected 18.
So I mean this is a difference. This is
really if they measure this this would
mean here that the orchestration made
with lang graph here is 18 times more
likely to fail because each routing
decision here is if you want a kind of a
new chance for the system to break
introduce some kind of error.
Now the workers come back and say what
we found in our testing is explained
here why the orchestration underperforms
and there are three reasons. The first
one is the orchestration fragments here
the reasoning process itself. So this
means if we go here with the
orchestrator it generates each turn
using only the current nodes prompt
template of course producing locally
reasonable but globally less coherent
responses. So this means at this very
particular moment in time and place when
node number 14 is now uh addressed now
and you gave it only here the current
node prompt template for this local
node. Somehow you miss out on the global
information of the complete system
dynamic. The orchestrator can maybe not
provide here the complete technical
overview or complete dependencies and
all the parameters and whatever and in
context baseline reasoning over the full
procedure holistically
maintaining here the awareness of where
the conversation has been and where it
needs to go. This sounds yeah I would
say okay I can go with this explanation.
Then they tell us the orchestration
itself introduces here failure modes and
the oras here and you have the further
detail in the study says the
orchestration itself adds three failure
categories they do not exist in the ICL
approach.
You have all the routing failures of
course you have as we just talked about
the decision ambiguity. You have
multiple edge condition that match maybe
simultaneously
and if you have not been really careful
you might have template conflicts. No.
So sometimes the current note
instruction may conflict with the
overall conversation context of what
happened three steps before where
suddenly we have we strengthen one
reasoning trace now and we weaken
another trace in this particular
formulation of the template. So we just
introduce more and more possible
mistakes. Now
so they also say that the orchestration
constraints not the model. So a note by
note template injection constrains the
frontier mall's natural conversational
style.
Okay. When you have at each node a
specific template for specific behavior,
yeah, you impose kind of if it's not
really coherent written, you impose kind
of a a little bit of touch different
notion. I understand this. An in context
baseline lets the model produce
unconstrained responses. the procedure
is in a prompt but the mall now really
chooses in total holistically how to
express it how to handle it and how to
deal with this. So I would say
reasonable absolutely. However, just be
clear there are limitations and you know
I always address limitation especially
in this study I showed I think we should
look at limitations because there are
two I would like to show you. They
address this here and they say our
comparison uses here a frontier model at
the time they did this a set 4.5 and
they say hm it could be if we use less
powerful models less capable models or
and this is now my integration here
heavily quantized models where say oh I
go down from an 8 bit quantization to a
4bit quantization
maybe now
this benefit here from the guardrails
that orchestration provides here
explicitly in the scaffolding in the
harness itself
is now compensating for a weaker
instruction following that the LLM
inherently has itself. So it means if
your model becomes less intelligent,
less powerful, less understanding, less
instruction following trains
heavily guantized, then those external
structure, those scaffolding might be
helpful to provide really guidelines
because those models simply do not have
the internal intelligence to solve the
task, give me the complexity themselves.
And I say okay yeah I agree with this
one.
So conclusion
again a quote here from the orus more
broadly this result suggests that as
frontiers models grow more and more
capable yes opus 4.7 maybe opus 5 we
will see soon the value of the external
scaffolding diminishes for a
well-defined task that the LLM has been
trained for and an ICL can really
perform well on I got it I say yes the
better we train the next generation of
AI models, the less scaffolding we maybe
need. However, if you want to have it
that you say you want to check this step
by step or you want to have this
external scaffolding, this harness
around that you really can have a
simpler debugging. I think it's still a
reason to have here this harness but you
see it is opening up. But is weakening
but this also means that the LLM itself
here is again a black box for us.
Okay. frameworks were built when models
needed more help or authors. But now our
current DI models might have outgrown
here the need for the scaffolding for
the AI harnessing and maybe we should
trust our LLMs more that they can really
follow the instruction following and
everything and perform here a beautiful
task.
Yes, of course. But this would limit us
here again to those global corporation
models. this I don't know trillion or or
trillion plus m sizes of free trainable
parameter that you cannot download
anymore to any local machine. You have
to invest $100,000 of dollars to be able
to run this here locally behind your
firewall or whatever you have. So it is
a pro and a con if you would develop
here into this dimension. But what is
really the most important is here and
this was just addressed on the site
because I I think it's important now
what they did and they they said
conversational procedures and this is
what they tested but if you read it
careful they simulated here for the
travel uh experiences here they
simulated all these conversations no so
whenever it is easy when you just have
ask questions gather information rack
system the making decision based on the
user input and follow a particular
flowchart that is provided in your
system prompt I think the paper really
proves that in context prompting is now
vastly superior to our orchestrated
agentic multi- aent whatever complexity
but careful you cannot simulate the
reality no we know from physics you can
simulate a lot of but reality is reality
and in reality ity you have maybe to
wait for an API or you have to wait for
a server response that is unknown or you
have to handle an unknown error no if
the server is down so you cannot
simulate everything
and they mention this rather on the side
note no that for the external tool
execution in reality which they did not
really test for as I told you hitting an
external API waiting for a server
response parsing here massive JSON
payload from a database or handling
these different error messages if
servers are down or whatever. Now, if
you really encounter the real world
problems that were not taken care about
here in the simulation, I think it can
be different.
So, I would agree for conversational
procedures the simulations were
beautiful. But if you have heavy tool
use, I know you might say, "But hey, all
these beautiful clawed models have been
trained for heavy tool use." Every new
model down to the smallest 4B mall has
been trained for agentic use, for
external tool execution. Every tiny
little new LLM knows exactly how to
handle at least 100 or 500 different
tools. This should also be possible with
our new LLM capabilities. But I just
want to notice clearly this is not
tested in reality.
So therefore we still have here for me
at least an open question mark. Is this
really value if you have heavy external
tool use or maybe in this particular
case then this whatever Google SDK open
SDK whatever you want to have for your
agent multi- aent coordination
orchestration maybe there's still a
reason why we need those guidelines
those safety restrictions
what do you think about it would be
interesting to get some feedback from
the community so careful whenever you
see the studies and you have beautiful
results. Just read it carefully exactly
what they have tested, what they have
not been tested for. And you know
reality is a different beast. You can
see you have beautiful simulation. Don't
get me wrong. But reality and simulation
it is still different. So careful but an
interesting development. Now suddenly
there is an indication maybe we don't
need this scaffolding. We don't need all
of this AI harnessing around because the
next generation of AI will have included
this in its original LLM capabilities.
I hope to see you in my next